A Guide to the Civil War Diary of Henry Thomas, 8th New York Heavy Artillery 1860-1866
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
Civil War Diary of Henry Thomas, 8th New York Artillery 1860-1866
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11409
3 x 4 1/2 inches, ca. 66 pages.
Thomas's diary covers the period from May 15 to June 9, 1864. Brief entries mention the Spotsylvania campaign; the battle of North Anna River' the Cold Harbor campaign and the death of his colonel P.A. Potter; and sharp shooting at Gaines' Mill and a truce to bury the dead. The end of the diary contains miscellaneous notes regarding days worked [at a blind asylum?], financial accounts, and names [of comrades?].
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: Alexander Autographs, Inc., Cos Cob, Connecticut, June 4, 1998.
Alternative Form
Transcription available.
Biographical/Historical Information
This unit was initially organized as the 129th New York Infantry at Lockport, New York, and mustered into federal service on August 22, 1862. It was sent to Baltimore, Maryland, and posted at Fort Federal Hill. In October 1862 its designation was changed to that of heavy artillery as the 8th New York Heavy Artillery. After garrison duty in Maryland and West Virginia during 1862-1864, the regiment was ordered to join the Army of the Potomac in Virginia in May 1864 and participated in its campaigns for the remainder of the war.
Scope and Content Information
This Civil War pocket diary, 1860, 1864 and 1866, of a Union soldier, Private Henry Thomas, Company G, 8th New York Heavy Artillery, includes entries during May 15 to June 9, 1864. During the period covered by the diary the regiment served in Virginia during Union General Ulysses S. Grant and the Army of the Potomac's spring campaign against the Army of Northern Virginia led by Confederate General Robert E. Lee which eventually culminated in the Petersburg siege. Near the end of the diary are entries for July 15, 1860 and 1866 of Thomas's accounts of days he worked; numerous and miscellaneous notes, names and financial accounts, in ink or pencil, are also present. This item measures 3 x 4 1/2 inches and contains ca. 66 pages; many of their contents are faint and illegible.
In brief entries Thomas recounts marching and building entrenchments during the Army's march to Richmond, Virginia; mentions by name several comrades including those killed or wounded; the disastrous attack at Cold Harbor, Virginia (June 3, 1864), and the rebels' refusal to honor a flag of truce to bury the dead (June 6, 1864). Two entries (June 1 and 2) bear the incorrect year "1863" which has been corrected to 1864 in this guide's typescript.
The flyleaf bears an inscription: "This Book Belongs to Henry Thomas, Batavia, [Genesee] County, New York." He identifies himself and his unit on a subsequent page as "Henry Thomas/Co. G 8th Artillery/Fourth Brigade/Division of the 2 [Second] Army Corps Army of the Potomac" followed by an undated list: "1 Blanket, 1 Cap, 1 Hat, Two [pair] drawers, One Vest, One Dress coat, One [pair] socks." The first major entry is a May 15, 1864 "On the Road to Richmond" letter: "Jim, I sent you a letter this morning telling you that we had got our marching orders well here we go for the Potomac Army/Hank." The next page bears an address, "St. James P. Thomas, Co. F, 94th Regiment, Annapolis, Maryland," apparently Henry Thomas's brother, Sergeant James P. Thomas [1841?-?], 94th New York Infantry.
James Thomas was promoted to the rank of First Lieutenant on August 12, 1864 and mustered out as a member of Company H, 94th New York. Frederick Phisterer, New York in the War of the Rebellion, 1861-1865(Albany: J.B. Lyon Company, State Printers, 1912), 4: 3064, 3078
Contents List
- Entry n.d. (Box 1)
  Left Baltimore on the 15th May arrived at Washington the same day. Left Washington on the 16th May down the Potomac River to Bells Plain [Belle Plain, Virginia] Staid all night left on the 17th for Fredericksburg arrived at F. C ? at four oclock on the march again marched to the [W]ilderness that Night and camped all Night.
- Entry May 18, [1864] (Box 1)
  Struck camp this morning at five oclock. On the move for the front. Heavy Musketry heard. We move up to the Right in the morning staid there one hour then moved up to the left. A few shells in among us but did no harm. I fell out but caught up to them about two miles from [Spotsylvania] Court House. In here the camp all night. [Spotsylvania Campaign, May 7-20, 1864]
- Entry May 19, 1864, Spotsylvania Court House (Box 1)
  Our Army is moveing up to the left the Rebs Retreat across the Po River last night. Our Regt is assigned to the [S]econd Corps Third Division Fourth Brigade of the Army of the Potomac. Our Corps took 9 nine thousand Prisoners yesterday. Two oclock we strike camp and move off about 60 sixty rods and move back again to the old ground. Five oclock Heavy Musketry heard off to the Right we double quick back into action loose two men killed and two wounded from our company. One shot through the Head and 1 through the Heart Wounded Parker [Private M. W. Parker] and Kerbey [Private Ezra Kirby] Battle of Pine Forest. Killed Glaser [Private Frank or Mathias Glaser] and Reed [Private John Reed]. [Spotsylvania Campaign: action at Harris' Farm, also known as Fredericksburg Road]
- Entry May 20th 1864 (Box 1)
  We drove the Rebs off the field and laid on our arms all Night. Ten oclock we camp on the Battlefield Horatio [Private Horatio Thomas?] has gone to Bury the Dead I felt kind O ? wished myself out of the fight but no go. Seven oclock at Night we draw six days rations and go and reenforce Battle.
- Entry May 21st 1864, Spotsylvania (Box 1)
  Twelve oclock midnight we start off towards Richmond. Traveled all night and next day. We crossed the River three miles the other side of Bowling Green there we build Intrenchments all Night.
- Entry May 22nd 1864, Bowling Green (Box 1)
  We are relieved this morning and go to the Rear we lay the [there] about two hours then move off to the Right and build intrenchments all the rest of that day. About four oclock ? Rowen [Corporal Nathaniel Rowan] brings the mail. For once in 8 eight days we slept over Night.
- Entry May 23rd [1864], Three Miles from Bowling Green (Box 1)
  Six oclock in the morning we take up the line of march again until we come to the Potomac River about five oclock in the afternoon we drove them from there [their] Rifle Pits we lay in the rear. About ten oclock we move up to the front and lay there the rest of the night. [Battle of the North Anna River, May 23-26, 1864]
- Entry May 24th [1864], North Anna River (Box 1)
  We now move to the Rear in the woods shells flying thick and fast heavy there until six oclock then move across the North Anna River. We get one man killed in crossing the River the rest of the troops advance on the Rebs we lay across the River to Night.
- Entry May 25th 1864, North Anna River (Box 1)
  We lay here all day. There is not much firing going on to day a few shells fall in among us. Eight oclock we recross the [Potomac] River and throw up intrenchments the rest of the Night.
- Entry May 26th 1864, North side of the North Anna River (Box 1)
  We lay here in the woods behind our intrenchments. Six oclock we support a Battery while it plays on the Rebs. Ten oclock we strike tents and march two miles farther down the [Pamunkey?] River there we lay to cover the Retreat of our Army.
- Entry May 27th [1864] (Box 1)
  We strike for City Point with ammunition for Buttler [General Benjamin F. Butler, 1818-1893]. Ten oclock we gone the train for city Point we march the Rest of the day without stopping
- Entry May 28th [1864] (Box 1)
  [O]n the Rode [road] to City Point nothing new more [then] we rest two hours last night are now crossing the Paypanoux [Pamunkey?] River. We go about two miles and camp for the Night.
- Entry May 29th [1864] Sunday Near Hanover Court House (Box 1)
  [W]e are now in camp the rest of the Army as far as can be seen are advancing on. We build intrenchments all that day and lay behind them that night.
- Entry May 30th [1864] Near White House Landing (Box 1)
  We show [sure] are on the march. We halt on what is called Prospect Hill. We lay hear [here] all day then build intrenchments that Night as the Rebs are trying to [repulse] our men.
- Entry May 31st [1864] Near White House Landing (Box 1)
  [W]e lay behind our intrenchments to day. Four oclock we leave our intrenchments and advance about 60 sixty rods to the edge of the Woods. I go down to the train and buy some [squab] for the Lieutenant and Colonel [Peter A. Porter, 1827?-1864]. Pork Tack [hardtack] Sugar and Beef.
  Phisterer, 2: 1396, 1398, 1413.
- Entry June 1st 1863 [1864] Near White House Landing (Box 1)
  We leave here for some parts farther down the towards Richmond and marched all Night of the 31st and all day of the first of June.
- Entry June 2nd 1863 [1864] Near Melvin [Malvern] Hill Va. (Box 1)
  [W]e now lay behind our entrenchments brisk firing in front of us. Two men wounded in my company. Dan King [Corporal Daniel W. Kinne] wounded through the thigh. Willson [Private Stephen Wilson] hit in the Back of the head with a piece of Shell. [Cold Harbor Campaign, May 31-June 12, 1864]
- Entry June 3rd 1864 Near Melvin [Malvern] Hill Va. (Box 1)
  Four oclock in the morning we are ordered to make a charge on the Rebs works we charge and lose six hundred men Killed and wounded. We did not take the works. We lost our Colonel P. A. Porter. The fight was called the fight Gains [Gaines] Hill. [The Federals' main--and failed--assault at Cold Harbor, June 3, 1864]
  "Col. Peters A. Porter died at the head of the 8th New York Heavy Artillery a few yards from the enemy's main position," Mark M. Boatner III, The Civil War Dictionary(New York: David McKay Company, Inc., 1959), 164. Nelson Armstrong, Nuggets of Experience: Narratives of the Sixties and Other Days, with Graphic Descriptions of Thrilling Personal Adventures(San Bernardino, California?: Times-Mirror P. and B. House, 1906) includes a group photograph of Colonel Porter and other officers of the New York Heavy Artillery on page 31 and a biographical sketch and references to his death, pp. 51-52, 83-84.
- Entry June 4th [1864] Gains Hill [Gaines' Mill] (Box 1)
  All quiet except a little Skirmish fire. We had to fall back under the Brow of the Hill. Peter A. Porters Body has not bin Recovered as yet.
- Entry June 5th [1864] Gains Hill [Gaines' Mill] (Box 1)
  Skirmishers firing all day. We still hold our works. Six oclock the Rebs make a charge on our lines and get as good as they give us. 9 oclock LeRoy Williams [Sergeant LeRoy Williams] and two others Recover the Body of our Colonel he had seven Balls in his Body.
  Sergeant LeRoy Williams [1844?-?] survived the war and was discharged as a first lieutenant on March 30, 1865. Phisterer 2: 1418.
- Entry June 6th [1864] Gains Hill [Gaines' Mill] (Box 1)
  All quiet except brisk Sharp Shooting got Shot at twice just now. We sent in a flag of truce to bury the dead but the Rebels would not [accept] of it. About six oclock they make a charge on our works but get all they want.
- Entry June 7th [1864] Gains Hill [Gaines' Mill] (Box 1)
  Brisk Sharp Shooting this morning. All quiet through the day. Four oclock in the [Evening] the Rebs [accept] our flag of truce to bury the [dead] the ground was covered with dead in front of the Rebs work Horatio [Private Horatio Thomas?] [traded] a knife for some tobacco with the Rebs.
- Entry June 8th 1864 Gains Hill [Gaines' Mill] (Box 1)
  All quiet this morning no firing our men and the Rebs are together and change [exchange] tobacco for [any] thing you have got.
- Entry June 9th 1864 Gains Hill [Gaines' Mill], 4th Brigade, 2nd Division 2nd Corps (Box 1)
  Nothing new this morning the same old story a continual fire from the sharp shooters.